<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/default.xsl"?>
<fr:tree xmlns:fr="http://www.forester-notes.org" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace" root="false" base-url="/">
  <fr:frontmatter>
    <fr:authors>
      <fr:author>Cal Newport</fr:author>
    </fr:authors>
    <fr:date>
      <fr:year>2016</fr:year>
      <fr:month>1</fr:month>
    </fr:date>
    <fr:uri>https://kellenkanarios.com/newportDeepWorkRules2016/</fr:uri>
    <fr:display-uri>newportDeepWorkRules2016</fr:display-uri>
    <fr:route>/newportDeepWorkRules2016/</fr:route>
    <fr:title text="Deep Work: Rules for Focused Success in a Distracted World">Deep Work: Rules for Focused Success in a Distracted World</fr:title>
    <fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon>
    <fr:meta name="bibtex"><![CDATA[@book{newportDeepWorkRules2016,
 title = {Deep {{Work}}: {{Rules}} for {{Focused Success}} in a {{Distracted World}}},
 author = {Newport, Cal},
 year = {2016},
 isbn = {978-1-4555-8666-0},
 publisher = {Grand Central Publishing},
 keywords = {Business & Economics / Skills,Business & Economics / Time Management,Business & Economics / Workplace Culture,Self-Help / Personal Growth / Success,Self-Help / Self-Management / Time Management},
 langid = {english},
 googlebooks = {4QTzCAAAQBAJ},
 abstract = {Millions of copies sold! The bestselling modern classic that sparked a worldwide conversation about the value of concentration---and the true costs of fractured attention. ``I'm handing you the answer to the overwhelm you feel, and his name is Dr. Cal Newport.'' ---Mel Robbins, The Mel Robbins Podcast, author of New York Times bestselling The Let Them TheoryDeep Work---the ability to focus without distraction on cognitively demanding tasks---is one of the most important abilities you can cultivate in our current moment. It's a skill that allows you to quickly master complicated information and produce quality results in less time. And yet, most people have lost the ability to go deep---spending their days in a frantic blur of emails, online meetings, social media, and AI slop, not realizing there's a better way. In Deep Work, bestselling author and professor Cal Newport makes the case for reclaiming focus as a critical skill in our digital world, providing step-by step instructions for achieving this goal, including four rules for transforming your daily habits: 1. Work Deeply 2. Embrace Boredom 3. Quit Social Media 4. Drain the Shallows A mix of cultural criticism and actionable advice, Deep Work offers a vitally important message: in our age of constant distraction, focus is a superpower. With inspiring examples and clear rules, Deep Work will teach you to introduce this ability in your own life.``As a presence on the page, Newport is exceptional in the realm of self-help authors \dots{} Six pages in, I powered down my laptop. Twenty pages in, I left the house to buy an alarm clock so that I wouldn't have an excuse to sleep next to my phone.''---Molly Young, The New York Times ``One of the few books I would call life-changing.'' ---Tim Maurer, Forbes ``I've read lots of books about productivity and lots of books about distraction. For me, Deep Work is among the best, on both counts.'' ---Joshua Rothman, The New Yorker ``[Deep Work] has changed how I live my life. Particularly, it's led me to stop scheduling morning meetings, and to preserve that time for more sustained, creative work.'' ---Ezra Klein, The Ezra Klein Show},
 month = {January},
 shorttitle = {Deep {{Work}}}
}]]></fr:meta>
  </fr:frontmatter>
  <fr:mainmatter />
  <fr:backmatter>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="References">References</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Context">Context</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Backlinks">Backlinks</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/kellenkanarios/" title="Kellen Kanarios" uri="https://kellenkanarios.com/kellenkanarios/" display-uri="kellenkanarios" type="local">Kellen Kanarios</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2026</fr:year>
              <fr:month>6</fr:month>
              <fr:day>24</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://kellenkanarios.com/7BUX/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>7BUX</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/7BUX/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="My Notes on Productivity">My Notes on Productivity</fr:title>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter><html:p>Due to the unstructured nature of PhD life / knowledge work in general, I have been trying to come up with the most effective system to ensure I am <fr:link href="/allenGettingThingsDone2015/" title="Getting Things Done: The Art of Stress-Free Productivity" uri="https://kellenkanarios.com/allenGettingThingsDone2015/" display-uri="allenGettingThingsDone2015" type="local"><html:em>Getting Things Done</html:em></fr:link> (ironically I found this system actually not that helpful).</html:p><html:p>Since <fr:link href="/calnewport/" title="Cal Newport" uri="https://kellenkanarios.com/calnewport/" display-uri="calnewport" type="local">Cal Newport</fr:link> is a professor (can relate to the knowledge work problem), I have been reading a lot of his stuff on productivity. I read <fr:link href="/newportDeepWorkRules2016/" title="Deep Work: Rules for Focused Success in a Distracted World" uri="https://kellenkanarios.com/newportDeepWorkRules2016/" display-uri="newportDeepWorkRules2016" type="local">Deep Work</fr:link> awhile back and the guiding principles make sense to me. However, I still struggle to actually implement it.</html:p><html:p>I often refer back to <fr:link href="/clearAtomicHabitsEasy2019/" title="Atomic Habits: An Easy &amp; Proven Way to Build Good Habits &amp; Break Bad Ones" uri="https://kellenkanarios.com/clearAtomicHabitsEasy2019/" display-uri="clearAtomicHabitsEasy2019" type="local">Atomic Habits</fr:link> as it intuitively just makes so much sense to me.</html:p><html:ul><html:li><html:em>Start small</html:em>: starting a habit should take less than 2 minutes.</html:li>
  <html:li><html:em>Never miss a habit twice</html:em>.</html:li>
  <html:li><html:em>Habit anchors</html:em>: I am always going to run so now after I run I stretch, which has resulted in remarkable stretching consistency (see my <fr:link href="/007S/" title="Weeknotes" uri="https://kellenkanarios.com/007S/" display-uri="007S" type="local">Weeknotes</fr:link>).</html:li>
  <html:li><html:em>Habit tracking:</html:em> Something I am also implementing in my <fr:link href="/007S/" title="Weeknotes" uri="https://kellenkanarios.com/007S/" display-uri="007S" type="local">Weeknotes</fr:link> with <fr:link href="https://kellenkanarios.com/habitify.me" type="external">habitify</fr:link>.</html:li></html:ul><fr:tree show-metadata="false"><fr:frontmatter><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link href="/kellenkanarios/" title="Kellen Kanarios" uri="https://kellenkanarios.com/kellenkanarios/" display-uri="kellenkanarios" type="local">Kellen Kanarios</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:date><fr:year>2026</fr:year><fr:month>6</fr:month><fr:day>25</fr:day></fr:date><fr:uri>https://kellenkanarios.com/OGCSJ/</fr:uri><fr:display-uri>OGCSJ</fr:display-uri><fr:route>/OGCSJ/</fr:route><fr:title text="My Current Workflow (constantly changing)">My Current Workflow (constantly changing)</fr:title></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><html:p>
I have been using <fr:link href="https://kellenkanarios.com/todoist.com" type="external">todoist</fr:link> and <fr:link href="https://kellenkanarios.com/habitify.me" type="external">habitify</fr:link>. I decided on these tools primarily because of their API availability. I wanted to be able to add / complete / see outstanding tasks or habits for the day without the allure of everything else my browser has to offer. Also visualization for my <fr:link href="/007S/" title="Weeknotes" uri="https://kellenkanarios.com/007S/" display-uri="007S" type="local">Weeknotes</fr:link>.
</html:p><html:ul><html:li>I had Claude write a little script to have my next tasks listed when clicked in my status bar, so I do not have to open the browser to check what I need to do today.</html:li></html:ul><html:p>
It seems how to properly use these (todoist in particular) is the subject of much debate. Here, I will outline what I converged to / works for ME right now. I have broken down my system into a hierarchy:
</html:p><html:ol><html:li>Higher level: how to actually choose what to do.</html:li>
  <html:li>Lower level: how to actually do the chosen task.</html:li></html:ol>
  <fr:tree show-metadata="false"><fr:frontmatter><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link href="/kellenkanarios/" title="Kellen Kanarios" uri="https://kellenkanarios.com/kellenkanarios/" display-uri="kellenkanarios" type="local">Kellen Kanarios</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:date><fr:year>2026</fr:year><fr:month>6</fr:month><fr:day>25</fr:day></fr:date><fr:title text="Figuring out what to do">Figuring out what to do</fr:title></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter>
  <html:p>
    This is effectively a task management system.
  </html:p>
  <html:p><html:strong style="font-family: var(--sans); font-weight: 500;">Work streams.</html:strong> I took this name from my investment banker friends (sounds cool / important). Basically, these are groupings I have made and allocated time for each day. They roughly consist of the following:
  </html:p>
    <html:ul><html:li>Research / work (4hrs first thing in the morning):</html:li>
      <html:ul><html:li>Active work towards new artifact or paper i.e. coding up ideas.</html:li>
        <html:li>In the absence of ideas, studying existing relevant papers.</html:li></html:ul>
      <html:li>Deliberate practice (2hrs after run / lunch):</html:li>
      <html:ul><html:li>Name taken from <fr:link href="/calnewport/" title="Cal Newport" uri="https://kellenkanarios.com/calnewport/" display-uri="calnewport" type="local">Cal Newport</fr:link>.</html:li>
        <html:li>As of writing this, a current example is spending ~2hrs a day writing / optimizing known kernels in CuTe / Pallas / NKI.</html:li>
        <html:li>Basically, something I need to understand or master for research that is not novel.</html:li></html:ul>
      <html:li>Extraneous Study (30min - 1hr):</html:li>
      <html:ul><html:li>Things not directly related to research, but I am curious about.</html:li>
        <html:li>I try to maintain study of related computer science fields. Primarily, studying a textbook in something like <fr:link href="/0084/" title="Notebook: Three Easy Pieces" uri="https://kellenkanarios.com/0084/" display-uri="0084" type="local">OS</fr:link>, <fr:link href="/P3GB/" title="Notebook: Inside the Machine" uri="https://kellenkanarios.com/P3GB/" display-uri="P3GB" type="local">computer architecture</fr:link>, etc.</html:li></html:ul>
      <html:li>Habits / daily upkeep (1hr normally end of day):</html:li>
      <html:ul><html:li>Mainly consists of reviewing Anki cards daily that come from extraneous study / deliberate practice.</html:li></html:ul></html:ul>
  </fr:mainmatter></fr:tree>
<html:p>
To decide on the next task, I use a priority-based system:
</html:p><html:ol><html:li>Things I will be working on today / until they are done. At most <html:strong>ONE</html:strong> thing per work stream.</html:li>
  <html:li>The <html:em>backlog</html:em> of things to do next</html:li>
  <html:ul><html:li>An index to find things to move to priority 1 for the next day</html:li> 
    <html:li>Keep relatively small to avoid the crippling nature of choice - roughly on the order of things I want done this week.</html:li></html:ul>
  <html:li>A larger backlog of things - should be completed in the next month or so.</html:li>
  <html:li>Things I am not working on right now, or have any need to be completed any time soon.</html:li></html:ol><html:p>
This idea is mainly based on the <fr:link href="/4WG5/" title="Multi-level feedback queue" uri="https://kellenkanarios.com/4WG5/" display-uri="4WG5" type="local">MLFQ</fr:link>, which has been proven effective for balancing response / turnaround time. To maintain this system, I have reviews each day and week (tracking with <fr:link href="https://kellenkanarios.com/habitify.me" type="external">habitify</fr:link>) to make sure I stay consistent.
</html:p>
 <html:div class="jms-callout" style="
  margin: 1em 0 1em 0.25em;
  padding: 0.5em 1.1em 0.5em 1.2em;
  border-left: 4px solid rgba(0, 100, 255, 0.7);
  border-radius: var(--radius);
  background-color: rgba(0, 100, 255, 0.05);
  "><html:span style="font-weight: 600; color: rgba(0, 100, 255, 0.7);">Algorithm.</html:span> 
  <html:em>Weekly review.</html:em>

 <html:div class="jms-callout" style="
  margin: 1em 0 1em 0.25em;
  padding: 0.5em 1.1em 0.5em 1.2em;
  border-left: 4px solid rgba(0, 100, 255, 0.7);
  border-radius: var(--radius);
  background-color: rgba(0, 100, 255, 0.05);
  "><html:span style="font-weight: 600; color: rgba(0, 100, 255, 0.7);">Algorithm.</html:span> 
  <html:em>Daily review.</html:em>
  <html:ul><html:li>For each work stream,</html:li>
    <html:ul><html:li>If I finished the allocated task for the day, get new task from priority 2.</html:li>
     <html:li>Else, do nothing and continue with the current task.</html:li></html:ul>
    <html:li>Review inbox and move new tasks to corresponding work stream for review on Friday.</html:li>
    <html:ul><html:li>If immediately important, can move directly to priority 1 / 2.</html:li></html:ul>
    <html:li>Look at calendar for next day and timeblock work streams for the next day.</html:li>
    <html:ul><html:li>Since PhD work is so hard to predict, I have found timeblocking any further than one day in advance to be a futile effort.</html:li></html:ul></html:ul>
  </html:div>

  <html:ul><html:li>Typically done on Fridays, so that I can dynamically allocate time on weekends if needed.</html:li>
    <html:li>For each work stream,</html:li>
    <html:ol><html:li>Look in remaining priority 2 and priority 3 tasks.</html:li>
     <html:li>Define what I think a successful week would look like (e.g. if I get all these things done next week I will be happy).</html:li>
     <html:ul><html:li>Look at calendar for week to guide this decision.</html:li></html:ul>
     <html:li>Get rid of at least two of those tasks (initial plan always too ambitious).</html:li>
     <html:li>Move / keep remaining tasks in priority 2.</html:li></html:ol>
    <html:li>Write <fr:link href="/007S/" title="Weeknotes" uri="https://kellenkanarios.com/007S/" display-uri="007S" type="local">Weeknotes</fr:link> for the week.</html:li></html:ul>
</html:div>

  <fr:tree show-metadata="false"><fr:frontmatter><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link href="/kellenkanarios/" title="Kellen Kanarios" uri="https://kellenkanarios.com/kellenkanarios/" display-uri="kellenkanarios" type="local">Kellen Kanarios</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors><fr:date><fr:year>2026</fr:year><fr:month>6</fr:month><fr:day>25</fr:day></fr:date><fr:title text="What to do when actually working on a task">What to do when actually working on a task</fr:title></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter>
  <html:p>
This is the harder part (and requires the most discipline). When working on a task, especially a more open-ended one like research, it is very common that a million other things come up that seem immediately important. All of the sudden, you have a great idea for the research project you haven't worked on in months. 
  </html:p>
  <html:p>
  It is <html:strong>crucial</html:strong> to collect and forget about these things until they are scheduled. This is the one thing I did take from <fr:link href="/allenGettingThingsDone2015/" title="Getting Things Done: The Art of Stress-Free Productivity" uri="https://kellenkanarios.com/allenGettingThingsDone2015/" display-uri="allenGettingThingsDone2015" type="local"><html:em>Getting Things Done</html:em></fr:link>. The system should <html:em>flow like water</html:em>. Making this achievable is where the todoist API becomes crucial.</html:p>
  <html:ul><html:li>I have a script bound by dwm that pops up vim for me to write down the task and, on save, it sends it to my inbox in todoist.</html:li>
    <html:li>I have more involved ones that allow me to actually allocate it to the specific work stream / priority if it is immediately obvious.</html:li></html:ul>
  <html:p>
  Another thing that I have found useful to actually achieving this watery flow is the <fr:link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique" type="external">pomodoro technique</fr:link>. This basically lets me gaslight myself into thinking I can go to the other things as soon as the timer ends (which is intentionally always just close enough). By the end, I often no longer have this urge and can continue on the scheduled tasks.
</html:p>
</fr:mainmatter></fr:tree>
</fr:mainmatter></fr:tree>
  <html:div class="comments">
    
  <html:hr />

    <html:script src="https://utteranc.es/client.js" repo="kkanarios32/website-comments" issue-term="pathname" theme="boxy-light" crossorigin="anonymous" async="" />
  </html:div>
</fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Related">Related</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Contributions">Contributions</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
  </fr:backmatter>
</fr:tree>
